Finding Aid for Imam Mohamad Jawad Chirri papers, 1959-2005
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Imam Mohamad Jawad Chirri papers 1959-2005
Chirri, Mohamad Jawad.
8.5 linear feet
2009063 Aa 2
Imam Mohamad Jawad Chirri was the director of the Islamic Center of America and the writer of many renowned works on Islam. The collection consists primarily of correspondence, newspaper clippings, photographs, memorandums, board minutes, writing drafts, publications and newsletters related to Chirri and the Islamic Center of America.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated in December 2008 by Adnan Jawad Chirri (donor no. 10144 ). Additions were received in November 2009.
Periodic additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Imam Mohamad Jawad Chirri was born in Lebanon on October 1, 1905. He was a graduate of the theological Institute of An-Najaf Al-Ashraf University in Iraq. In 1948, the small Muslim community in the Detroit area invited Imam Chirri to the United States of America. As the spiritual leader to the primarily Lebanese-American community, Imam Chirri envisioned the construction of a new mosque which would help strengthen the local Muslim population as well as enlightened non-Muslims throughout America on the practices of Islam.
In 1959, a little over a decade after arriving in America, Imam Chirri traveled to Egypt seeking financial assistance for the construction of the mosque he envisioned for the growing Detroit area Muslim community. While in Egypt, Imam Chirri met with President Jamal Abdul Nasser who provided the Islamic Center with a donation large enough to purchase land on Joy Road and Greenfield. During his visit to Egypt, Imam Chirri also met with Sheikh Mahmood Shaltut, Imam of the Al-Azhar University of Cairo. The two spiritual leaders participated in lengthy discussions about the similarities between Shi-ite Jaafari and Sunnite. After their discussions, Imam Shaltut made the historic announcement declaring the equality between the Shi-ite Jaafari and Sunnite Schools.
Three years after his trip to Egypt, the Islamic Center of Detroit (which would later be renamed the Islamic Center of America) opened its doors in 1962. The new center and mosque allowed for weekly Sunday services and became the social center of the strengthening community.
Along with being the founder of the Islamic Center of America, Imam Chirri was a renowned author and lecturer. Imam Chirri published widely in Arabic, but the self-taught English speaker also wrote many celebrated works in English. Some of his writings include Inquiries About Islam, The Faith of Islam, and Imam Hussein, Leader of the Martyrs. His writings and position as the director of the Islamic Center of America made Imam Chirri a widely sought after authority on Islam. His views and insights on topics related to Islam and the Muslim community were often quoted in the national media.
Over a decade after Imam Mohamad Jawad Chirri's death in 1994, the Islamic Center of America opened a new center on Ford Road in 2005. The new center is the home of one of largest mosques in North America.
The Imam Mohamad Jawad Chirri Papers document the cleric's religious, leadership, and scholarly activities as well as the inner workings of the Islamic Center during Chirri's tenure and after his death. The collection consists primarily of correspondence, newspaper clippings, photographs, memorandums, board minutes, writing drafts, publications and newsletters. The material is generally in English, unless otherwise noted. The collection contains the following series: Imam Mohamad Jawad Chirri, Islamic Center of America, Zehia Kahil and Publications.
Subjects:
Arab World Festival.; Chirri, Mohamad Jawad.; Federation of Islamic Associations in the U.S.A. & Canada.; Islam--United States.; Islamic Center of America (Dearborn, Mich.); Imams (Mosque officers)--Michigan.; Kahil, Zehia.; Muslim women--United States.; Muslims--United States.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Chirri, Mohamad Jawad.; Islamic Center of America (Dearborn, Mich.); Muslims--United States.
Contributors:
Kahil, Zehia.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Imam Mohamad Jawad Chirri
  Imam Mohamad Jawad Chirri series reflects Chirri's significant role in shaping and managing the Islamic Center of America and his scholarly contributions to the study of Islam. The series consists primarily of correspondence, newspaper clippings, photographs, writing drafts, and publications. The series contains two subseries: Personal/Background, and Writings, Drafts and Notes.
  - Personal/Background
    The Personal/Background subseries includes newspaper clippings, correspondence, and photographs reflecting Chirri's standing as an authority on Islam and a guiding figure at the Islamic Center of America.
    - Business and membership cards undated (Box 1)
    - Commemorations on the death of Imam Mohamad Jawad Chirri 1994-2003 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, Arabic, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, English 1959-1993, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Lebanese Cedar Medal 1991 (Box 1)
    - Newspaper clippings on Chirri 1966-1998 (Box 1)
    - Notes/Notebook, Arabic undated (Box 1)
    - Portraits and Photographs of Chirri at ICA and other events, undated (Box 1)
    - United States Citizenship and Passport 1957-1977 (Box 1)
  - Writings, Drafts and Notes
    The Writings, Drafts and Notes subseries documents the development of Chirri's celebrated writings. The material is generally undated, unless otherwise noted. The drafts have been organized by title and usually contain multiple edited versions of the particular writing rather than the published version. The titles are listed alphabetically under English Titles, Arabic Titles, or Notebooks. English Titles indicates that the drafts are written in English, whereas Arabic Titles indicates that the drafts are written in Arabic. The series also contains thirty-eight of Chirri's notebooks. The notebooks are primarily in Arabic and contain drafts and notes for sermons and book chapters. When more than one title is listed this indicates that the notebook is a combined volume and contains multiple drafts or book chapters.
    - Book Lists 1975-1981 (Box 1)
    - Book List undated (Box 1)
      (in Arabic)
    - Library Addresses and Correspondence 1983-1984 (Box 1)
    - Address to the Lions and Rotary Club 1967 (Box 1)
    - Hadith Writings for book undated (Box 1)
    - Sermons undated (Box 1)
    - Lecture Notes 1967-1969, undated (Box 1)
      (in English)
    - Lecture Notes 1957, 1966-1971, undated (Box 1)
    - Questions for Newspaper Column 1967-1968 (Box 1)
    - Writing Draft Fragments undated, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Titles in English
      - "About the Islamic Schools of Thought" (Box 1)
      - "The Book of Islam" (Box 1)
      - "Chapter I: A light on the history of the Prophethood" (Box 1)
      - "Chapter I: A Uniting Force" (Box 1)
      - "Chapter II: Mohammed the Prophet of the Universal Religion" (Box 1)
      - "Chapter V: A Criterion of the True Religious Principles" (Box 1)
      - "Chapter VI: The Second Principle of Islam" (Box 1)
      - "Chapter VIII: Justice of God" (Box 1)
      - "Chapter VIII: Man is the Master of his Actions" (Box 1)
      - "Chapter VIII: The Prophethood of Mohammed" (Box 1)
      - "Chapter IX: Man is the Master of his Actions" (Box 1)
      - "The Creation of Life" (Box 1)
      - "The Creator by His free will, not by Necessity" (Box 1)
      - "Dear American Friends" (Box 1)
      - "Determination" (Box 1)
      - "The Directive of the Imam Ali to Malik-el Ashter" (Box 1)
      - "The Divine Justice in His Laws" (Box 1)
      - "Early Political Difference between the Muslims" (Box 1)
      - "Economical Justice" (Box 1)
      - "The electoral convention" (Box 1)
      - "The Faith of Islam," 1964, 1979 (Box 1)
      - "Fasting in Islam" (Box 1)
      - "The first principle in Islam" (Box 1)
      - "The flexibility of the Islamic Laws" (Box 1)
      - "God" (Box 1)
      - "God, of Islam, is ever-living, never dies" (Box 1)
      - "God, of Islam, is not dead" (Box 1)
      - "God's being" (Box 1)
      - "The growth of Islam" (Box 1)
      - "Have you known that Al-Azhar recognized the Shi-ite Jaafari Mazhab as equal to the Sunni Mazhab?" (Box 1)
      - "The Historical Declaration of His Eminence, Sheikh AL-Azhar Mahmoud Shaltut" (Box 1)
      - "The Imam Hussein: Leader of the Martyrs" (Box 1)
      - "The Imams from the relatives of Mohammad and their followers" (Box 1)
      - "Immortality" (Box 1)
      - "Inquire and think freely, Islam advises" (Box 1)
      - "Inquiries on Islam" (Box 1)
      - "Islamic Teachings in the form of Questions and Answers," 1961 (Box 1)
      - "Jesus in Islam" (Box 2)
      - "The Just God" (Box 2)
      - "Life After Death" (Box 2)
      - "Man is a free Agent" (Box 2)
      - "Man's Purity and Height" (Box 2)
      - "The Meaning of Islam" (Box 2)
      - "One God" (Box 2)
      - "The Originator of the Universe" (Box 2)
      - "Pilgrimage in Islam" (Box 2)
      - "Prayers in Islam" (Box 2)
      - "Preface" I (Box 2)
      - "Preface" II (Box 2)
      - "Prohibitions in Islam or its Commandments" (Box 2)
      - "The Prophet of Islam" (Box 2)
      - "The Prophethood" (Box 2)
      - "Question and Answer" (Box 2)
      - "A statement" (Box 2)
      - "A statement of the Islamic Principles" (Box 2)
      - "To George Romney..." (Box 2)
      - "Unfulfilled Will of the Prophet" (Box 2)
      - "Universality (?)" (Box 2)
      - "When I met...Sheikh Al-Azhar" (Box 2)
      - "The Wise" (Box 2)
      - "The Wise administrator" (Box 2)
    - Titles in Arabic
      - "Abi Bakr's Era," Omar's Era," The Perfect Protestor," "The Mother of the Pius," "Consensus," "Othman," (Box 2)
      - "About the Various Sects of Islam" (Box 2)
      - "Abu Baker Follows" (Box 2)
      - "Al Shura--Consensus" (Box 2)
      - "Consensus" (Box 2)
      - "During Omar's Time" (Box 2)
      - "During the Time of the Caliphs" (Box 2)
      - "Islam and Christianity: a comparison" (Box 2)
      - "Materialism and Spirituality" (Box 2)
      - "Muslims as a Political Minority" (Box 2)
      - "On Occasion of Ramadan Approaching" (Box 2)
      - "The perfect opposition" (Box 2)
      - The Prophetic Plan (Box 2)
      - "Questions" (Box 2)
      - "Should succession be by vote or by a prophetic creed" (Box 2)
      - "Unfulfilled Will of the Prophet" (Box 2)
      - "The Various Forms of Government and its Virtue" (Box 2)
    - Notebooks
      (in Arabic, unless otherwise noted)
      - Book, untitled (Box 2)
      - General Notes in English (Box 2)
      - Notes on "Al Saqeef (?) and its termination and questions," "The Imam's position," and "Response to the 4th question about the Prophet's administration" (Box 2)
      - Notes on Ali's Position (Box 2)
      - Notes on Ali's Special Attributes (Box 2)
      - Notes on Chirri's politics (Box 2)
      - Notes on the Birth of the Imam (Box 2)
      - Notes on the Prophet's family position (Box 2)
      - Notes "On those with the original role, part II," and notes on Islam of the Imam (Box 2)
      - "About the legend" (Box 2)
      - "After the Prophet's will -- Prophet's will does not get implemented," and "The fulfillment of the Prophet's will" (Box 2)
      - "Ahl al Bayt's Status in Islam-Battle of Safayn" (Box 2)
      - "Al Shura" from Consensus, part III (Box 2)
      - "Argument" (in English), and "Who are 'Ahlel el Bayt' (Prophet's Kin)" (Box 2)
      - "Ayat Al Tableegh (the message)," "Who is the Prophet," "The Prophet declares his Brother Ali, XII," and "The Prophet's confident, part VI" (Box 2)
      - "Battle of Busra" (Box 3)
      - "Battle of Busra, part XXIII," and "Ablution (Wudu') Prayer" (Box 3)
      - "Battle at Safayn was it inevitable?," and Sermons 1975 (Box 3)
      - "Conclusion, part II" (Box 3)
      - "Def: Al Shura = consensus or agreement," "Abdel Rahmanibn Araf Al Shura, part II" and "Prophet Mohammad's family, part I" (Box 3)
      - "During Omar's Time," (Box 3)
      - "Failure of the Imam, part II" (Box 3)
      - "The four questions surrounding the election of Abi Bakr, part II" (Box 3)
      - "Fulfillment of the prophet's will" (Box 3)
      - "Fulfillment of the prophet's will," and "Ahel el Bayts role in Islam, part I" (Box 3)
      - "The Imam's judgment style was it like a king?, part XXX," (Box 3)
      - "Imam's Failure, part II," "Conclusion, part I (Box 3)
      - "The myth of the conspiracy, part XXIV," and "The Prophet's kin in Islam" (Box 3)
      - "Othman's Time" (Box 3)
      - "Othman's Time, part II," and "Loyalty--The Imam," (Box 3)
      - "The Prophet's personality," "The Prophet's successor -- death of the Prophet," and "Should the Caliphate or successor be by appointment or by vote" (Box 3)
      - "A Prophet's will does not get implemented, (page 190-223)" (Box 3)
      - "A Prophet's will does not get implemented, (page 224-626)" (Box 3)
      - "Shahada of the Imam," "Imam's responsibility to Muslims," and "Bearers of the original role, part I" (Box 3)
      - "Should the Caliphate be decided by vote, prophecy or by kin?" (Box 3)
      - "Status of Ahl Al Bayt (Prophet's family), part I" (Box 3)
      - "Those with the original role and the arrival of Ali, part II," "The first Muslims, part IV," "Radio Talks 10/10/1976" and "Talks at Islamic Center in Detroit, 1975" (Box 3)
      - "Who are the Prophet's Kin?" (Box 3)
      - "Why did the Imam fail, part XXXI" (Box 3)
- Islamic Center of America
  Islamic Center of America series documents over 40 years of the Islamic Center of America's administrative services and community activities. The series includes correspondence, flyers, photographs, religious material, and reports. The series contains three subseries: Administrative, Activities, and Subject Files.
  - Administrative
    The Administrative subseries contains background material related to the overall functioning of the Center including board minutes, contribution and donor lists, financial statements, reports, community surveys, laws and guidelines. The contribution and donor lists have been included in the collection because they provide an indication of active persons involved with the Center; however, it is important to note that the contributors may have asked that their donations not be recorded believing that God does not want humans showing their charity. The sub-series also documents the planning, construction, and completion of the Grand Mosque and new Islamic Center of America building on Joy Road.
    - General Background undated (Box 3)
    - "A statement presented to the Chairman, present and previous members of the Board of Trustees of the Islamic Center of America, May Allah bless them all; from Mohamad Baker Chirri, servant of the Muslims and brother of the founding Imam," undated (Box 3)
    - Agreements and Warranties 1982-1988 (Box 3)
    - Board of Directors 2004 (Box 3)
    - Board of Trustees 1975-2004 (Box 3)
    - Board of Trustees Correspondence 1986-1995, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Community Address Lists undated (Box 4)
    - Community Survey 1994 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, Arabic, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, English 1975-2003, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Donation Acknowledgement
      - 1990 (Box 4)
      - 1992 (Box 4)
      - 1993 (Box 4)
      - 1994 (Box 4)
    - Donation Pledges 1963 (Box 4)
    - Donor Addresses 1970 (Box 4)
    - Financial Reports and Balance Sheets
      - 1970s (Box 4)
      - 1980s (Box 4)
      - 1991 (Box 4)
      - 1992 (Box 4)
      - 1993 (Box 4)
      - 1994 (Box 4)
      - 1995 (Box 4)
      - 1996 (Box 4)
      - 1997 (Box 4)
      - 1998 (Box 4)
      - 1999 (Box 4)
      - 2000s (Box 4)
    - Financial Statements 1962-1975 (Box 4)
    - Fundraiser Invitations and Memorandums 1971-1999 (Box 4)
    - Fundraising Dinner Contribution List
      - 1970s, 3 folders (Box 4)
      - 1983 (Box 4)
      - 1984 (Box 4)
      - 1985 (Box 4)
      - 1986 (Box 5)
      - 1987 (Box 5)
      - 1988 (Box 5)
      - 1989 (Box 5)
      - 1990, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - 1991, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - 1992 (Box 5)
      - 1993 (Box 5)
      - 1994 (Box 5)
      - 1995 (Box 5)
      - 1996 (Box 5)
      - 1997, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - 1998 (Box 5)
      - 1999 (Box 5)
    - Grand Mosque, Ground Breaking Ceremony Photographs undated (Box 5)
    - Grand Mosque, Planning and Completion 1996-2005, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Lebanese-Relief Fund, Contribution List 1976 (Box 5)
    - Reports, Laws, Guidelines 1962-1990 (Box 5)
    - Specifications for ICA on Joy Road undated, 5 folders (Box 6)
  - Activities
    The Activities subseries contains newspaper clippings, religious material, event announcements, and memorandums and petitions on political and social issues affecting the Muslim community abroad. The subseries reflects the Islamic Center of America's involvement within the Detroit/Dearborn community.
    - Dr. Syedna Mohammed Burhanuddin Address 1978 (Box 6)
    - Event Announcements 1969-2003, 6 folders (Box 6)
    - Outside Events and Organizations 1980s (Box 6)
    - Inmate Correspondence 2001-2003 (Box 6)
    - Lebanon Crisis Correspondence and Petition 1996, 2 folder (Box 6)
    - Marriage Contracts, English 1969-1984, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Marriage Contracts, Arabic (Box 6)
    - Mourning Forms 1984-1992, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Newspaper clippings on ICA and Islam in Detroit/Dearborn Area 1972-1998, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Newspaper clippings on Islam, general 1984-2002 (Box 7)
    - Newspaper clippings, Arabic, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Photographs of ICA Community undated (Box 7)
    - Prayers in Arabic undated (Box 7)
    - Prayers in English 1978 undated, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Religious Instruction undated (Box 7)
    - Social and Political Causes 1974-1992 (Box 7)
    - Social Causes, Mailgrams 1972-1982 (Box 7)
    - Youth Associations 1969-2005, 2 folders (Box 7)
      (includes "Lessons for Moslem Children")
    - Misc. Documents in Arabic, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Subject Files
    The Subject Files subseries contains files from the Islamic Center of America, which contains correspondence and other documents from the Center's multiple religious leaders as well as a file containing correspondence documenting the Center's search for a librarian. The sub-series contains a file with material originating from Imam Chirri causing some overlap with the Imam Mohamad Jawad Chirri series.
    - Imam Berro 1987-1989 (Box 7)
    - Imam Hassan Habhab 1988-1995, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Imam Jawad Chirri 1983-1994, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Imam Mohammad Ali Elahi 1992-1994, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Imam Sayel El-Katat 1989-1990 (Box 8)
    - Khalil Alawan 1992-1995 (Box 8)
    - Librarian Recruitment 1986-1988 (Box 8)
- Zehia Kahil
  Zehia Kahil series documents the activities of the first Muslim woman to be elected the head of an Islamic organization. The series contains correspondence, notes, meeting agendas and minutes, and newspaper clippings from organizations in which Kahil held an administrative position. The organizations represented in the series include the Arab World Festival, Federation of Islamic Associations, and the Order of the Eastern Star.
  - Arab World Festival
    - Correspondence 1973-1976 (Box 8)
    - News Releases, Fact Sheets, Programs 1974-1976 (Box 8)
    - Agendas and Meeting Notices 1974-1976 (Box 8)
    - Minutes 1973-1974, 3 folders (Box 8)
  - Federation of Islamic Associations
    - Newspaper clippings 1972-1981 (Box 8)
    - Constitution, Laws and Meetings 1968-1973 (Box 8)
    - Mailings 1969-1978 (Box 8)
    - Convention Material 1971-1977 (Box 8)
    - Notes and Attendance Lists undated (Box 8)
    - Correspondence 1967-1975, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Order of the Eastern Star 1962-1967 (Box 8)
- Publications
  Publications series contains newsletters and publications created or collected by the Islamic Center of America. Many of the publications are newsletters from outside Islamic associations primarily from North America but also from abroad. Some of the newsletters are more complete than others. For example, the series contains a very comprehensive collection of the Muslim Star but contains only two issues of the Palestine Digest. The series also contains booklets and scholarly publications on Islam.
  - Islamic Center of America Publications 1988-2000, 5 folders (Box 8)
  - Muslim Star, 1964-1982, 11 folders (Box 8)
  - Islamic Center of America (ICCA) Newsletter, 1990-1993 (Box 9)
  - Al-Fajr: Islamic Service Organization Newsletter, 1969-1974 (Box 9)
  - The Bulletin of the Islamic Center of New York, 1973-1974 (Box 9)
  - The Bulletin of the Islamic Center of Washington, D.C., 1972-1980, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Facts: Bulletin of the Lebanese Association for Information on Palestine, 1974-1975 (Box 9)
  - Islam Canada 1972-1974 (Box 9)
  - Impact 1974 (Box 9)
  - Islamic Items 1972-1975 (Box 9)
  - Palestine Digest 1974-1975 (Box 9)
  - The Link, 1973, 1987 (Box 9)
  - Al Urdun, 1978, 1981 (Box 9)
  - Misc. Islam Organizations' Newsletters 1964-1990, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Misc. Publications on Islam 1960s-1970s (Box 9)
  - Publications in Arabic (Box 9)
  - Published Lectures 1971-1983 (Box 9)
  - Qur'an and Woman by Amina Wadud-Muhsin, 1992 (Box 9)
  - Shi'ite Encyclopedia by Hassan Al-Amin, 1965-1966 (Box 9)
  - Book 5: "Life of the Prophet" from A Series of Islamic Books for Children, 1970 (Box 9)